[Music]
The next day was rainy and dark. Rain fell on the roof of the barn and dripped
steadily from the eaves.
Rain fell in the barnyard and ran in crooked courses down into the lane where
thistles and pigeed grew.
Rain spattered against Mrs. the Zuckerman's kitchen windows and came
gushing out of the down spouts. Rain fell on the backs of the sheep as they
grazed in the meadow.
When the sheep, tired of standing in the rain, they walked slowly up the lane and
into the fold.
Rain upset Wilbur's plans.
Wilbur had planned to go out this day and dig a new hole in his yard. He had
other plans, too. His plans for the day went something like this. Breakfast at
6:30. Skim milk crusts, middlings, bits of donuts, wheat cakes with drops of
maple syrup sticking to them, potato skins, leftover custard pudding with
raisins, and bits of shredded wheat.
Breakfast would be finished at 7:00.
From 7 to 8, Wilbur planned to have a talk with Templeton, the rat that lived
under his trough. Talking to Templeton was not the most interesting occupation
in the world, but it was better than nothing. From 8 to 9, Wilbur planned to
take a nap outdoors in the sun. From 9 to 11, he planned to dig a hole or
trench and possibly find something good to eat buried in the dirt.
From 11 to 12, he planned to stand still and watch flies on the boards, watch
bees in the clover, and watch swallows in the air. 12:00 lunchtime, middlings,
warm water, apple pairings, meat gravy, carrot scrapings, meat scraps, stale
homonyy, and the wrapper off a package of cheese. Lunch would be over at 1:00.
From 1 to 2, Wilbur planned to sleep.
From 2 to 3, he planned to scratch itchy places by rubbing against the fence.
From 3 to 4, he planned to stand perfectly still and think of what it was
like to be alive, and to wait for Fern.
At 4 would come supper. Skim milk, proender, leftover sandwich from Lurvy's
lunchbox, prune skins, a morsel of this, a bit of that, fried potatoes, marmalade
drippings, a little more of this, a little more of that, a piece of baked
apple, a scrap of upside down cake.
Wilbur had gone to sleep thinking about these plans. He awoke at 6 and saw the
rain, and it seemed as though he couldn't bear it.
"I get everything all beautifully planned out, and it has to go in rain,"
he said. For a while he stood glooily indoors. "Then he walked to the door and
looked out. Drops of rain struck his face. His yard was cold and wet. His
trough had an inch of rainwater in it.
Templeton was nowhere to be seen. Are you out there, Templeton? Called Wilbur.
There was no answer.
Suddenly, Wilbur felt lonely and friendless.
"One day just like another," he groaned.
"I'm very young. I have no real friend here in the barn. It's going to rain all
morning and all afternoon, and Fern won't come in such bad weather. Oh,
honestly. And Wilbur was crying again for the second time in 2 days. At 6:30,
Wilbur heard the banging of a pale.
Lurvy was standing outside in the rain, stirring up breakfast. "Come home, pig,"
said Lurvy. Wilbur did not budge. Lurvy dumped the slops, scraped the pail, and
walked away. He noticed that something was wrong with the pig.
Wilbur didn't want food. He wanted love.
He wanted a friend, someone who would play with him. He mentioned this to the
goose, who was sitting quietly in a corner of the sheepfold. "Will you come
over and play with me?" he asked. Sorry, Sunny. Sorry, said the goose. I'm
sitting sitting on my eggs. Eight of them. Got to keep them toasty, oyst.
I have to stay right here. I'm no flippity ibity give it. I do not play
when there are eggs to hatch. I'm expecting gosslings.
Well, I didn't think you were expecting woodpeckers, said Wilbur bitterly.
Wilbur next tried one of the lambs.
"Will you please play with me?" he asked. "Certainly not," said the lamb.
"In the first place, I cannot get into your pen as I am not old enough to jump
over the fence." In the second place, I am not interested in pigs. Pigs mean
less than nothing to me.
What do you mean less than nothing?
replied Wilbur. I don't think there is any such thing as less than nothing.
Nothing is absolutely the limit of nothingness. It's the lowest you can go.
It's the end of the line.
How can something be less than nothing?
If there were something that was less than nothing, then nothing would not be
nothing. it would be something even though it's just a very little bit of
something. But if nothing is nothing, then nothing has nothing that is less than it is.
Oh, be quiet, said the lamb. Go play by yourself. I don't play with pigs.
Sadly, Wilbur lay down and listened to the rain. Soon he saw the rat climbing
down a slanting board that he used as a stairway. "Will you play with me,
Templeton?" asked Wilbur. "Play," said Templeton, twirling his whiskers. "Play?
I hardly know the meaning of the word."
"Well," said Wilbur, "it means to have fun, to frolic, to run and and skip and make merry."
I never do those things. if I can avoid them, replied the rat sourly. I prefer
to spend my time eating, knowing, spying, and hiding. I am a glutton, but
not a merry maker. Right now, I'm on my way to your trough to eat your
breakfast, since you haven't got enough sense to eat it yourself." And Templeton
the rat crept stealthily along the wall and disappeared into a private tunnel
that he had dug between the door and the trough in Wilbur's yard.
Templeton was a crafty rat, and he had things pretty much his own way. The
tunnel was an example of his skill and cunning. The tunnel enabled him to get
from the barn to his hiding place under the pig trough without coming out into
the open. He had tunnels and runways all over Mr. Zuckerman's farm, and could get
from one place to another without being seen.
Usually he slept during the daytime and was abroad only after dark.
Wilbur watched him disappear into his tunnel. In a moment he saw the rat's
sharp nose poke out from underneath the wooden trough. Cautiously, Templeton
pulled himself up over the edge of the trough. This was almost more than Wilbur
could stand on this dreary rainy day to see his breakfast being eaten by
somebody else. He knew Templeton was getting soaked out there in the pouring
rain, but even that didn't comfort him.
Friendless, dejected, and hungry, he threw himself down in the manure and sobbed.
Late that afternoon, Lurvy went to Mr.
Zuckerman. I think there's uh something wrong with that pig of yours. He hasn't
touched his food. Give him two spoonfuls of sulfur and a little molasses, said
Mr. Zuckerman. Wilbur couldn't believe what was happening to him when Lurvy
caught him and forced the medicine down his throat. This was certainly the worst
day of his life. He didn't know whether he could endure the awful loneliness anymore.
Darkness settled over everything.
Soon there were only shadows and the noises of the sheep chewing their cuds
and occasionally the rattle of a cow chain up overhead.
You can imagine Wilbur's surprise when out of the darkness came a small voice
he had never heard before. It sounded rather thin but pleasant. "Do you want a
friend, Wilbur?" it said. "I'll be a friend to you."
"I've watched you all day, and I like you." "But I can't see you," said
Wilbur, jumping to his feet. Where are you and who are you? I'm right up here,
said the voice. Go to sleep. You'll see me in the morning.
Chapter 5.